Hey everyone and thanks for dropping
back into the cryptoverse.
Today we're going to talk about Bitcoin.
Where in the cycle are we? If you guys
like the content, make sure you
subscribe to the channel, give the video
a thumbs up, and check out the sale on
Into the Cryptoverse Premium at into the
cryptoverse.com.
As a reminder, we do have the ITC
conference coming up, the Investing
Through the Cycles Conference. That'll
be taking place in November. or the main
day of the conference will in fact be
November 21st in Miami, Florida. So,
make sure you guys get your ticket. The
ticket prices will be increasing on
September 1st. So, make sure you get
your ticket before then if you really
want to go. You can find the tickets at
benjaminc.com and then just go to the
conference tab. Link will be in the
description below. Now, we do this
video, you know, I don't know, once
every six months, once every 12 months,
something like that. But the idea is
just to say where in the cycle are we?
And at any given point we could be in a
bull market. We could be in a bare
market. But we do this video regardless
of whether it's a bull market or a bare
market because we are objective, right?
We do not
dismiss an asset because it goes into
into a bare market. We do not, you know,
cry cry crazy crazy things uh euphoric
stuff in bull markets. We try to be
rational investors. Now, there's a few
that I think have lost their way this
bare market because they have kind of
repeated the same idea, the same the
same sort of tired idea that if Bitcoin
is is subject to a four-year cycle, then
why ever invest in it? But the simple
retort to that is the stock market has
four-ear cycles as well. And you can
pretty clearly see these four-ear cycles
throughout history where the lows occur
approximately every four years or so.
But yet buying index funds like you know
that track the S&P for the last hundred
years is one of the better investments
you could have ever made. So, the idea
that Bitcoin isn't a good investment
because it follows a four-year cycle is
just simply untrue. In fact, it is the
four-year cycle that we can see observed
throughout a lot of history. Even in the
stock market in recent years, you'll
notice that you'll have lows
approximately every four years. You have
2022. You also have 2018. Yeah, we had a
black swan pandemic where it went lower,
but you ignore that. You can still see
lows occurring approximately every four
years.
The four-year cycle does not
mean that assets that follow it are
useless.
It just means there's this human
psychology behavior, this liquidity
aspect,
presidential cycle that that impacts the
way in which the asset moves during
certain times of that cycle. But that
doesn't diminish the fact that the the
asset can in fact be a good asset even
if it goes through a bare market. I
don't know of a single asset that goes
up and to the right forever without
occasional occasionally going down. One
of the few things that I could think of
that generally goes up and to the right
without ever going down is the US
national debt. Okay. But apart from
that, you're going to be hardressed to
find too many things that only ever go
up. Um, and you know, and and so I I
just want people to be aware of that.
Now, where are we in the current cycle?
Before we get into the the charts on the
platform
from a more from a broader view, you can
see that Bitcoin tops approximately
every four years. It also bottoms
approximately every four years as well.
Now, will this break eventually? Yeah.
Like, it it probably will, and we'll be
there to talk about it when it does. But
the point is is you would have gone
insane over the last decade and a half
saying that it was going to break. And
if you just assumed it wasn't going to
break, you would have been much more
successful than anyone who thought it
was going to. And despite the cries for
crazy price predictions in the at the
end of 2025,
the time came and came and went without
those euphoric price predictions coming
true. And so the argument is that
you don't need to try and be really
really smart to outsmart what Bitcoin's
doing. Just look at what the chart is
telling you. And I defer to it. You can
see the same chart that I can see,
right? And we see lows approximately
every four years. We see highs
approximately every four years. That
doesn't mean you have to have lower lows
or lower highs. Doesn't mean you have to
have higher highs or higher lows. What
it means is that approximately every
four years a low in the market forms.
Approximately every four years a high in
the market forms. The four-year cycle
does not refer to the highs in the
market. It refers to the lows. The highs
could be translated. You could have I
mean if if in the last cycle Bitcoin had
topped in say 2024 instead of 2025 and
then just slowly came down, you could
still argue the four-year cycle would be
intact if the low still formed near the
end of 2026. The four-year cycle tells
you when the bottoms tend to occur.
So if you were to break these cycles up,
you can get an idea of where in the
cycle are we. The first thing we're
going to look at is measuring every
cycle from the low. So in this case,
measuring the 2017 cycle from the 2015
low, the very beginning of 2015,
measuring the 2021 bull market from the
2018 low, measuring the prior bull
market from the 2022 low,
you get the idea. And when you do that,
you get a chart that looks like this.
What's fascinating, absolutely
fascinating, is that two cycles ago, we
topped on day 1,069.
Last cycle we topped on day 1,059
right really I guess it was 168 or so
the cycle four so 168 1,059 and then
this past cycle topped on day like,50 so
within about a a week or two right of
topping and Bitcoin topped basically
when it always tops despite
proclamations that this time would be
different the people that meet in the
mental gymnastics club on Twitter were
in wrong. And now they can realize that,
hey, perhaps we don't have to go to the
mental gymnastics club and we can just
simply say that Bitcoin topped when it
always tops. It does not matter that
there was not a rotation into altcoins.
It does not matter that we did not have
a euphoric rally that led to that
rotation. What matters is that it tops.
It topped when it always does.
But if you want to join the mental
gymnastics club,
they're always accepting new members.
Now,
from this point, we say, well, when did
the last couple of cycles bottom? Well,
if you look at two cycles ago, it
bottomed on day 1432. Last cycle about
1436. We're currently on day 1354.
We're getting pretty close. And I can
practically guarantee you that the
biggest critics of the 4-year cycle are
highly likely to become the biggest
cheerleaders of it in just a couple of
months once it aligns with their bias.
Once it aligns, they'll be happy to talk
about the four-year cycle. They're only
unhappy to talk about it this year and
quick to criticize those that do because
they've been on the wrong side of the
market and they want to find a reason
for why it's wrong. But if you just
deferred to the four-year cycle, you
would have been on the right side of
this bare market the entire way down.
Okay.
So, as measured from the low,
day 1354
of cycles that normally take 1430 to
1440 days. Pretty close to starting a
new cycle. Doubtful that it started yet,
right? Like we could still go a little
bit lower. Doubtful. I mean, I'm not no
guarantees, right? I mean, I said just
if you start DCAing Bitcoin in the
second half of the midterm year, you're
probably going to be fine long term. Not
financial advice. You're probably going
to be fine long term. But in the short
term, it would be foolish to ignore the
fact that in the last two bare markets,
we had capitulations that occurred a
little bit later in the year. So, let's
measure Bitcoin from the peak. Now, you
really shouldn't do this, but we're
going to do it anyways. Why? Because we
speculate
dubiously on this channel. And when you
measure Bitcoin from the high, you can
see this bare market has not been as bad
as the last three bare markets. Probably
because we didn't top on Euphoria, so
there wasn't as many retail participants
panic selling. But still, the bare
market has come regardless. And right
now, we're actually well above where we
normally are at this time. In fact, if
you were to average out the last three
bare markets and compare it to the
current one, you can see what I'm
talking about, right? Like you can see
where we are in the purple line relative
to the average of the last several.
You can see that on average the bottom
occurs uh on day 406 or so and we're
currently on day 304.
So about 34s of the way through the bare
market on average. Now, if you were to
compare this to the having, which is not
something we compare it to that
frequently, but I know there's a few
people that like to compare it from the
having. If you go from one having to
another, what you'll notice is that
during this time, Bitcoin has always
been sort of trending down or somewhat
weak. The last two bare markets after
those after the the peaks from the
havingss, you can see Bitcoin was
trending down. During the same time in
after the first having, Bitcoin had
bottomed already, but it still didn't go
anywhere, right? It still just hugged
the lows for a year. And on some
exchanges, you see this drop right here
on day 1000. On some exchanges, that
drop was actually a lower low, right?
And on on this index here, it might have
even been a lower low. You can see right
here the low on January 15th was
actually 166, but the act the low in
August was actually 162. So even in that
case, Bitcoin still didn't really go
anywhere. And technically on some
exchanges didn't even bottom until
further out. So I'm looking at this
chart thinking, all right, we're still
doing what we normally do. You know, if
history is an indication, the market's
going to stay weak for a few more
months. And there's nothing wrong with
that, right? Like we've already been in
a bare market for 10 months. What's a
couple more months now? Is there a
guarantee that Bitcoin comes out of it
in the next couple of months and goes
into a bull market?
No. Maybe Bitcoin bottoms sooner than
October. Maybe it bottoms in September.
Maybe Bitcoin doesn't bottom until
December, right? But the point is is
that the prior bare markets have all
lasted about a year. And so that's why I
said October. And now you have everyone
sort of laughing at it like well if Ben
think if Ben thinks it's October and
he's telling this to all these people
then it can't abs it can't be October.
Maybe they're right. Like maybe they're
right. But I will say in Q4 of last year
we said that that was likely the top and
it was. So again, you know, I I struggle
with it too sometimes. I'm like, do I do
I want to go join the mental gymnastics
club and and and participate
or do I just want to say, well, if it's
wrong, let the market prove that it's
wrong. And if it's wrong, then so be it.
But my guess is that Bitcoin will bottom
when it normally bottoms. And if you if
you kind of look at the range, that
would probably be like late September
through mid December is normally when
you would expect it to bottom. In 2018,
it didn't bottom till December. Last
cycle it bottomed in November.
Three cycles ago it bottomed I believe
in January.
So
well hold on a second. Yeah. I mean
think about that. If you take this as
the low,
think about it. We went from a January
bottom.
We're going to speculate dubiously,
right? to a December bottom
to a
November bottom.
Why not October? I mean, why not? I
again, I I know the Mental Gymnastics
Club's having a field day with it, but
why not?
Could very well be October.
We'll see, right? We'll see if it plays
out like that. I will say if it is
October, it would be hilarious because
then it's like it just played out like
every other bare market and everyone
just overco complicated it. But you
know, you look at it as measured from
the peak, from the bottom, from the
having and it all aligns. You measure it
from the presidential terms compared
compare Bitcoin and Trump's second term
to to Joe Biden. Guess what was
happening? We're at the same draw down
that we're at right now during Biden's
term. And guess what? You had a little
bit of a rally. you came back down and
then you set your market cycle bottom
and the next bull market began. So it
seems to me like no matter how you
measure it, every chart is saying the
same thing. When you look at the
year-to- date ROI of Bitcoin when
instead of from a cycle view, from sort
of a seasonal view in 2026,
you can see that it's more of like a
less volatile version of 2018. The lows
align with each other, the lower highs
align. It it looks pretty similar.
And if you compare 2026 to the average
of prior midterm years and overlay one
standard deviation to that average,
we're still within one standard
deviation ban of the average of the last
three midterm years.
So
for me, Bitcoin's doing what it always
does, and maybe that'll change. But
people are like, well, why does the
stock market keep going to new alltime
highs? Why can't Bitcoin follow?
Bitcoin never follows the stock market
in midterm years. Even in 2018, like you
know, you guys remember what Bitcoin did
in 2018? It dropped a lot that year. The
stock market,
if you look at the stock market, there
were two corrections in 2018, right? Two
corrections.
But when you look at a yearly candle in
2018, it wasn't that bad for the stock
market, right? like it it really wasn't.
The stock market dropped 6%.
In 2018,
Bitcoin dropped 73%.
So, so what if the stock market goes up
and Bitcoin doesn't? That's what
happened in 2019 as well, right? like in
2019, which arguably from a macro
perspective is the best comparison
because Bitcoin topped out in June of
2019, a couple of months before
quantitative tightening ended in in
August and there was no rotation into
alts and also there were three rate cuts
from the Federal Reserve that year.
So this is the only other the sort of
the main one you could compare it to is
the 2019 one if you want to over think
about the business cycle. Now, there are
some guys that have a problem with the
four-year cycle because they believe
it's only the business cycle, but the
reality is both can be true. You
basically have Bitcoin operating within
a four-year cycle that's also operating
within a business cycle. And if people
would if people could understand that
that like the reason there was no
rotation into altcoins at the end of the
last four year cycle, it was because we
were in this macro regime from 2019 when
there was also no rotation into
altcoins.
So 2025 and 2019 fundamentally are
really similar. Bitcoin topped about two
months where QT ended in both cases.
Bitcoin topped in the year there were
three rate cuts around the same time.
Bitcoin topped and there was no rotation
into altcoins and Bitcoin topped on
apathy where social interest was
trending down and Bitcoin dominance was
trending up. So if you want to compare
it to 2019, you can do that. That's my
favorite thing to do. My point is I'm
saying that this downtrend in Bitcoin
after the apathetic top in 2019 just
happens to align with the 2026 bare
market.
That's the point. That's what I am sort
of trying to communicate here as to as
to what's happening with Bitcoin in in
this midterm year. And I could be wrong.
Like I'm not I'm not going to sit here
and say that it it has to play out like
this. you know, you could have a rally
before you go down. I mean, you know, I
don't really expect a pandemic like
drop. But if you want to compare 2019 to
the current bare market, you could do
that as well and say that look, all
right, well, you know, we had this we
had this draw down, we had a little
rally, we continue to put in a new low,
but the problem is is back then you
could argue that we bottomed because we
had price-based capitulation. We haven't
really had that. we've had where we're
looking more at timebased capitulation
which normally takes about a year to
play out. So where in the cycle are we?
I would say we are in the back 30% of
the of the bare market. We're getting
close to the end of the bare market, but
we still might have a little bit further
to go. I don't think that accumulation
is bad, right? Like I'm not saying you
can't go buy Bitcoin. What I'm simply
saying is that look, have a strategy if
you're going to buy, which I think is
fine, right? Right? If you're going to
buy, I started buying a little bit back
when we went below 60K. If you're going
to buy, so what, right? Like, I mean,
who cares if it goes lower later in the
year, it probably will, but that doesn't
mean you can't start thinking about how
do you how do you get positioned
potentially for the next bull market.
And that's my point. I started buying
Bitcoin in the summer of 2022. And guess
what? Later that year, I got wrecked.
Six months later, I didn't care. I
started buying Bitcoin in the summer of
2018. Guess what? Six months later, I
got wrecked. Six months after that, I
didn't care at all. So, if your time
horizon is 3 months, then maybe don't
buy an asset that's going to be very
volatile. But if your time horizon is
long enough, it doesn't really matter.
So, my point in this in this video is to
say, look, we are nearing the end of the
bare market.
history would suggest we might not be
quite there yet, but we're we're nearing
the end of it.
And so, it's important to keep that in
mind when people are talking about why
this time is different. Because I would
say any one of those people that dunk on
the four-year cycle and think that this
time is different, if you had told them
in October that Bitcoin would have been
trading below 60K
in the in the midterm year, they would
have been like, "All right, the four-ear
cycle was right." But because it's just
slowly gone down, people have a way of
convincing themselves that something
different is happening. When in reality,
the same thing has happened. In fact, if
you look at it in terms of moving
averages, you can see the same thing
like the 50 to the 100 to the 200. Every
cycle, you first go below the 50 week,
then you go to the 100, then you go to
the two, then the next 50, 100, 2, then
the next 50, 100, then we went slightly
below the 200. Guess what? again 50 100
now we're slightly we're right around
that 200 week moving average. This the
same thing, right? You can't look at
this chart and say this time is
different. It played out the exact same
way it's played out the last three bare
markets is that once you lose the 50
then you lose the 100 then you go to the
200 and maybe we go a little bit lower
right last cycle we even went to like
the 300 or something but the point is is
it's not different. So, I
will be skipping the mental gymnastics
club meeting and I'm going to say, you
know what, I think this time is not
different. And
that's my view. If I'm wrong, I'm wrong.
But you see why I'm saying this, right?
Like, it's not like I'm just, you know,
coming up with this out of nothing. You
guys have the same, you guys can see the
same charts that I'm looking at. I'm not
hiding them. I'm showing you guys these
charts and so I've figured out what I
think is going to happen. I've
communicated that. I have my own DCA
strategy in place and I hope it works
out and I hope it works out for you guys
as well. For those that have been
impacted by some of the hacks recently,
I I truly feel for you. I don't really
think that's fair for a lot of people.
They they did what they thought was
right. They still lost money. It sucks.
the the industry has a long way to go to
mature because a lot of people are not
going to differentiate between Bitcoin
and the hardware wallet that people use
the store. They're just going to think
the whole thing's a scam. So, as an
industry, we still have a long way to
go. There's a reason why people are are
leaving crypto and not coming towards
it. That doesn't mean that Bitcoin is a
scam. Bitcoin is just going through a
bare market like it always has and like
it will in the future. And that doesn't
mean there's anything wrong with it. It
just means that it is subject to the
same human psychology that makes up the
four-year cycle in other markets like
the S&P 500. If you guys like the
content, make sure you subscribe to the
channel, give the video a thumbs up, and
again, check out the sale on into the
cryptoverse premium at into the
cryptoverse.com if you guys want to
follow along with those charts. And we
got the conference coming up in Miami.
And guess when it is? It's in late
November. The reason I picked late
November, I was thinking one of two
things. I'm like, well, the low is
either going to be in or it's not. I
think there's a good chance the low will
be in by late late November, especially
if we bottom out in like late September
or like late October, you know, or in
that in that window. If it if we don't
bottom then and we go a little bit
lower, like if we continue to follow
2018 and the bottom doesn't fall out
until November, like you see in 2018,
the bottom fell out mid November, we
would we would also be pretty close to
the bottom. So, what I'm thinking is at
this conference, we're going to be
pretty close to the low if it's not
already in. And so, hopefully at the
conference, we can have a rational
discussion of what that means for
Bitcoin from that point going forward.
We love to have you guys there. Ticket
prices are going up on September 1st, so
make sure you guys get your ticket. We
still have space um uh for the for
people to go to the party on the the
lower paid tier, but the space is
quickly running out. So, if you do want
to go to the party, make sure you guys
get a ticket uh sooner rather than
later. Thank you guys for tuning in.
Subscribe and I'll see you guys next
time.